What is radiation therapy
and what to expect?
Introduction
While you may have heard of chemotherapy
and surgery to treat cancer,
Radiation therapy is often less well known
and talked about far
less in popular media.
This video will discuss what external beam
radiation therapy is, its role in
treating cancer, and what you can expect
in your radiation treatment journey.
Cancer occurs when cells in your body
start to grow too fast
and in an uncontrolled way, without any
checks or balances on their growth.
The unchecked growth of these cells
lead to tumors that cause symptoms
you may be feeling or cause your otherwise
healthy organs to malfunction.
There are three main tools that doctors
use to combat the cancer cells
to stop them from growing,
or to kill them all together.
These are One: Systemic Treatments,
which go throughout your body
system, such as chemotherapy
or immunotherapy.
Two: Surgery and three: Radiation.
Chemotherapy uses medications or
chemical compounds
to kill the unwanted cancer cells,
and immunotherapy boosts your body's
own immune system to fight the cancer.
Targeted drugs are precision treatments
that single out specific molecular components important to cancer cell growth.
Surgery is the physical removal
of those cells from the body.